Wonder by RJ palao part six August what a piece of
work is a man how Noble in reason how infinite in faculty in form and moving
how Express and admirable in action how like an angel in apprehension how like a
god the beauty of the world Shakespeare Hamlet North Pole THE SPUD LAMP WAS a big hit
at the science fair. Jack and I got an A
for it. It was the first A Jack got in any class all year long, so he was
psyched. All the science fair projects were set up on tables in the gym. It was
the same setup as the Egyptian Museum back in December, except this time there
were volcanoes and molecule diaramas on the tables instead of pyramids and
pharaohs. And instead of the kids taking our parents around to look at everybody
else’s artifact, we had to stand by our tables while all the parents wandered
around the room and came over to us one
by one. Here’s the math on that one 60 kids in the grade equals 60 sets of
parents— —and doesn’t even include grandparents. So that’s a minimum of 120
pairs of eyes that find their way over
to me. Eyes that aren’t as used to me as
their kids’ eyes are by now. It’s like how compass needles all always point north,
no matter which way you’re facing. All those eyes are compasses, and I’m like
the North Pole to them. That’s why I still don’t like school events that
include parents. I don’t hate them as much as I did at the beginning of the
school year. Like the Thanksgiving Sharing Festival: that was the worst one,
I think. That was the first time I had to face the parents all at once. The
Egyptian Museum came after that, but that one was okay because I got to dress up
as a mommy and nobody noticed me. Then came the winter concert, which I totally
hated because I had to sing in the chorus. Not only can I not sing at all,
but it felt like I was on display. The New Year Art Show wasn’t quite as bad,
but it was still annoying. They put up our artwork in the hallways all over the
school and had the parents come and check it out. It was like starting school
all over again, having unsuspecting adults pass me on the stairway. Anyway,
it’s not that I care that people react to me. Like I’ve said a gazillion times:
I’m used to that by now. I don’t let it
bother me. It’s like when you go outside and it’s drizzling a little. You don’t
put on boots for a drizzle. You don’t even open your umbrella. You walk through
it and barely notice your hair getting wet. But when it’s a huge gym full of
parents, the drizzle becomes like the total hurricane. Everyone’s eyes hit you
like a wall of water. Mom and Dad hang around my table a lot, along with Jack’s
parents. It’s kind of funny how parents actually end up forming the same little
groups their kids form. Like my parents and Jack’s and Summer’s mom all like and
get along with each other. And I see Julian’s parents hanging out with
Henry’s parents and Miles’s parents. And even the two Max's parents hang out
together and so funny. I told Mom and Dad about it later when we were walking home,
and they thought it was a funny observation. I guess it’s true that like seeks like, said
Mom the Auggie doll FOR A WHILE the “war” was all we talked
about. February was when it was really at its worst. That’s when practically nobody
was talking to us, and Julian had started leaving notes in our lockers then notes
to Jack were stupid, like: You stink, big cheese! and Nobody likes you anymore! I
got notes like: Freak! And another that said: Get out of our school,
orc! Summer thought we should report the notes to miss Ruben who was the middle
school dean, or even Mr. Tushman, but we thought that would be like snitching.
Anyway, it’s not like we didn’t leave notes, too, though ours weren’t really
mean. They were kind of funny and sarcastic.
One was: You’re so pretty, Julian! I love you. Will you marry me? Love Biola Another
was: Love your hair! XOX Bula Another was: You’re a babe. Tickle my feet. XO
bua Bula was a madeup person that me and Jack came up with. She had really gross
habits, like eating the green stuff in between her toes and sucking on her
knuckles. And we figured someone like that would have a real crush on Julian,
who looked and acted like someone in a kids spot commercial. There were also a
couple of times in February when Julian, Miles, and Henry played tricks on Jack.
They didn’t play tricks on me, I think, because they knew that if they got
caught “bullying” me, it would be big time trouble for them. Jack, they figured, was
an easier target. So one time they stole his gym shorts and played Monkey in the-
Middle with them in the locker room room Another time Miles, who sat next to Jack
and Home Room swiped Jack’s worksheet off his desk, crumpled it in a ball, and
tossed it to Julian across the room. This wouldn’t have happened if Miss Bossa had
been there, of course, but there was a substitute teacher that day, and subs
never really know what’s going on. Jack was good about this stuff. He never let
them see he was upset, though I think sometimes he was. The other kids in the
grade knew knew about the war. Except for Savannah's group, the girls were neutral
at first. But by March they were getting sick of it. And so were some of the boys.
Like another time when Julian was dumping some pencil sharpener shavings
into Jack’s backpack, Amos who's usually tight with them, grabbed the backpack out
of Julian’s hands and returned it to Jack. It was starting to feel like the
majority of boys weren’t buying into Julian anymore. Then few weeks ago, Julian
started spreading this ridiculous rumor that Jack had hired some Hitman to “get”
him and Miles and Henry. This lie was so pathetic that people were actually
laughing about him behind his back. At that point, any boys who had still been
on his side now jumped ship and were clearly neutral. So by the end of March,
only Miles and Henry were on Julian’s side— —and I think even they were getting
tired of the war by then.
I’m pretty sure everyone stopped playing the Plague game behind my back, too. No
one really cringes if I bump into them anymore, and people borrow my pencils
without acting like the pencil has cooties. People even joke around with me
now sometimes. Like the other day I saw Maya writing a note to Ellie on a piece
of ugly doll stationer and I don’t know why, but I just kind of randomly said: “Did
you know the guy who created the ugly dolls base them on me?” Maya looked at me
with her eyes wide open like she totally believed me. Then, when she realized I was
only kidding, she thought it was the funniest thing in the world. “You are so
funny, August!” she said, and then she told Ellie and some of the other girls what I
had just said, and they all thought it was funny, too. Like at first they were
shocked, but then when they saw I was laughing about it, they knew it was okay
to laugh about it, too. And the next day I found a little ugly doll keychain
sitting on my chair with a nice little note from Maya that said: For the nicest
Auggie Doll in the world EXO Maya 6 months ago stuff like that would never
have happened, but now it happens more and more. Also, people have been really
nice about the hearing aids I started wearing lobot EVER SINCE I was little, the
doctors told my parents that someday I’d need hearing aids. I don’t know why this
always freaked me out a bit: maybe because anything to do with my ears
bothers me a lot. My hearing was getting worse, but I hadn’t told anyone about it.
The ocean sound that was always in my head had been getting louder. It was
drowning out people’s voices, like I was underwater. I couldn’t hear teachers if I
said in the back of the class. But I knew
if I told Mom or Dad about it, I’d end up
with hearing aids— —and I was hoping I could make it through the fifth grade
without having that happen. But then in my annual checkup in October I flunked
the audiology test and the doctor was like, “Dude, it’s time.” And he sit me to a
special ear doctor who took impressions of my ears. Out of all my features, my
ears are the ones I hate the most.
They’re like tiny close fists on the sides of my face. They’re too low on my
head, too. They look like squashed pieces of pizza dough sticking out of the top
of my neck or something. Okay, maybe I’m exaggerating a little. But I really hate
them. When the ear doctor first pulled the hearing aids out for me and Mom to
look at, I groaned. “I am not wearing that thing,” I
announced, folding my arms in front of me.
“I know they probably look kind of big,” said the ear doctor, “but we had to attach
them to the headband because we had no other way of making them so they’d stay
in your ears.” See, normal hearing aids usually have a part that wraps around
the outer ear to hold the inner buds in
place. But in my case, since I don’t have outer ears, they had to put the earbuds
on this heavyduty headband that was supposed to wrap around the back of my
head. “I can’t wear that, Mom,” I whined.
“You’ll hardly notice them,” said Mom, trying to be cheerful. “They look like headphones.”
“Headphones? Look at them, Mom!” I said angrily I look like
lot Which one is Lobot?” said Mom calmly.
“Lobot?” The ear doctor smiled as he looked at the headphones and made some
adjustments. The Empire Strikes Back? The bald guy with the cool bionic radio
transmitter thing that wraps around the back of his skull?” “I’m drawing a blank,”
said Mom. “You know Star Wars stuff?” I asked the ear doctor no Star Wars stuff?”
he answered, slipping the thing over my head. “I practically invented Star Wars
stuff!” He leaned back in his chair to see how the headband fit and then took it
off again. “Now, Auggie, I want to explain what all this is,” he said, pointing to the
different parts of one of the hearing aids. “This curved piece of plastic over
here connects to the tubing on the ear mold. That’s why we took those impr back
in December, so that this part that goes inside your ear fits nice and snug. This
part here is called the tone hook, okay?
And this thing is the special part we’ve attached to this cradle here.” “The Lobot
part,” I said miserably. “Hey, Lobot is cool,” said the ear doctor. “It’s not like we’re
saying you’re going to look like Jar Jar, you know? That would be bad.” He slid the
earphones on my head again carefully.
“There you go, August. So how’s that?” “Totally comfortable I said. “You’ll
get used to them very quickly,” he said. I looked in the mirror. My eyes started
tearing up. All I saw were these tubes jutting out from either side of my head— —like
antennas. “Do I really have to wear this, Mom?” I said, trying not to cry. “I hate them.
They don’t make any difference!” “Give it a second budy said
the doctor. “I haven’t even turned them on yet. Wait until you hear the difference:
you’ll want to wear them.” “No I won’t!” And then he turned them on hearing
brightly HOW CAN I describe what I heard when the doctor turned on my hearing
aids? Or what I didn’t hear? It’s too hard
to think of words. The ocean just wasn’t living inside my head anymore. It was
gone. I could hear sounds like shiny lights in my brain. It was like when
you’re in a room where one of the light bulbs on the ceiling isn’t working, but
you don’t realize how dark it is until someone changes the light bulb and then
you’re like, whoa, it’s so bright in here!
I don’t know if there’s a word that means the same as “bright” in terms of
hearing, but I wish I knew one, because my ears were hearing brightly now. “How does
it sound doggie said the ear doctor. “Can you hear me me okay, buddy?” I looked at
him and smiled but I didn’t answer.
“Sweetie, do you hear anything different?” said Mom. “You don’t have to shout, Mom.” I nodded
happily. “Are you hearing better?” asked the ear doctor. “I don’t hear that noise
anymore,” I answered. “It’s so quiet in my ears.” “The white noise is gone,” he said,
nodding. He looked at me and wait I told you you’d like what you heard,
August.” He made more adjustments on the left hearing aid. “Does it sound very
different, love?” Mom asked. “Yeah.” I nodded.
“It sounds lighter.” “That’s because you have bionic hearing now, buddy,” said the ear doctor,
adjusting the right side. “Now touch here.” He put my hand behind the hearing aid. “Do
you feel that? That’s the volume. You have to find the volume that works for you.
We’re going to do that next. Well, what do you think?” He picked up a small mirror
and had me look in the big mirror at had the hearing aids looked in the back. My
hair covered most of the headband. The only part that peaked out was the tubing.
“Are you okay with your new bionic Lobot hearing aids?” the ear doctor asked,
looking in the mirror at me. “Yeah,” I said. “Thank you.”
“Thank you so much, Dr. James,” said Mom. The first day I showed up at school with the
hearing aids, I thought kids would make a big deal about it. But no one did. Summer
was glad I could hear better, and Jack said it made me look like an FBI agent
or something. But that was it. Mr Brown asked me about it in English class, but
it wasn’t like, what the heck is that thing on your head?! It was more like, “If
you ever needed me to repeat something, Auggie, make sure you tell me,
okay?” Now that I look back, I don’t know
why I was so stressed about it all this time. Funny how sometimes you worry a lot
about something and it turns out to be nothing via's secret A COUPLE OF days
after spring break ended, Mom found out that Via hadn’t told her about a school
play that was happening at her high school the next week. And Mom was mad. Mom
doesn’t really get mad that much (though Dad would disagree with that), but she was
really mad at Via for that. She and Via got into a huge fight. I could hear them
yelling at each other in Via’s room. My bionic Lobot ears could hear Mom saying:
“But what is with you lately, Via? You’re moody and taciturn and
secretive. “What is so wrong with my not telling you about a stupid play?” Via
practically screamed. “I don’t even have a speaking part C in it!” “Your boyfriend
does! Don’t you want us to see him in it?”
“No! Actually, I don’t!” “Stop screaming!” “You scream first! Just leave me alone, okay?
You’ve been really good about leaving me alone my whole life, so why you choose
high school to suddenly be interested I have no idea. Then I don’t know what Mom
answered because it all got very quiet, and even my bionic Lobot ears couldn’t
pick up a signal my cave BY DINNER THEY seemed to have
made up. Dad was working late. Daisy was sleeping. She’d thrown up a lot earlier
in the day, and Mom made an appointment to take her to the vet the next morning.
The three of us were sitting down and no one was talking. Finally, I said: “So, are we
going to see Justin in a play?” Via didn’t answer but looked down at her
plate. “You know, Auggie,” said Mom quietly.
“I hadn’t realized what play it was, and it really isn’t something that would be
interesting to kids your age.” “So I’m not invited?” I said, looking at
Via. “I didn’t say that,” said Mom. “It’s just
I don’t think it’s something you’d enjoy you get totally bored,” said Via,
like she was accusing me of something. “Are you and Dad going?” I asked
dad will go,” said Mom. “I’ll stay home with
you.” “What FIA yelled at Mom. “Oh great, so you’re going to punish me for being
honest by not going?” “You didn’t want us to go in the first place, remember?”
answered Mom. “But now that you know about it, of course I want you to go!” said Via.
“Well, I’ve got to weigh everyone’s feelings here, Via,” said Mom. “What are you
two talking about?” I shouted. “Nothing!” they both snapped at the same time. “Just
something about via school that has nothing to do with you,” said Mom. “You’re
lying,” I said. “Excuse me?” said Mom, kind of shocked. Even Via looked
surprised. “I said you’re lying!” I shouted.
“You’re lying!” I screamed at Via, getting up. “You’re both liars! You’re both lying
to my face like I’m an idiot!” “Sit down, Auggie!” said Mom, grabbing my arm. I pulled
my arm away and pointed at Via. “You think I don’t know what’s going
on?” I yelled. “You just don’t want your brand new fancy high school friends to
know your brother’s a freak!” “Auggie!” Mom yelled. “That’s not true!” “Stop lying to me,
Mom!” I shrieked. “Stop treating me like a baby! I’m not I know what’s
going on!” I ran down the hallway to my room and slammed the door behind me so
hard that I actually heard little pieces of the wall crumble inside the door
frame. Then I plopped onto my bed and pulled the covers up on top of me. I
threw my pillows over my disgusting face and then piled all my stuffed animals on
top of the pillows, like I was inside a little cave. If I could walk around with
a pillow over my face all the time, I
would. I don’t even know how I got so mad.
I wasn’t really mad at the beginning of
dinner. I wasn’t even sad. But then all of a sudden it all kind of just exploded
out of me. I knew Via didn’t want me to
go to her stupid play. And I knew why. I figured Mom would follow me into my room
right away, but she didn’t. I wanted her to find me inside my cave of stuffed
animals, so I waited a little more, but even after 10 minutes she still didn’t
come in after me. I was pretty surprised.
She always check on me when I’m in my room, upset about stuff. I pictured Mom
and Via talking about me in the kitchen.
I figured Via was feeling really, really, really bad. I pictured Mom totally laying
on the guilt. And Dad would be mad at her
when he came home, too. I made a little hole through the pile of pillows and
stuffed animals and peaked at the clock on the wall. Half an hour had passed and
Mom still hadn’t come into my room. I tried to listen for the sounds in the
other rooms.
Were they still having dinner? What was going on? Finally, the door opened. It was
Via. She didn’t even bother coming over to my bed, and she didn’t come in softly
like I thought she would. She came in quickly goodbye AUGGIE,” SAID VIA “Come
quick. Mom needs to talk to you.” “I’m not apologizing!” “This isn’t about you!” she
yelled. “Not everything in the world is about you, Auggie! Now hurry up.
Daisy’s sick. Mom’s taking her to the emergency vet. Come say
goodbye.” I pushed the pillows off my face and looked up at her. That’s when I saw
she was crying. “What do you mean ‘goodbye’?” “Come on!”
she said, holding out her hand. I took her hand and followed her down the hall to
the kitchen. Daisy was laying down sideways on the floor with her legs
stray out in front of her. She was panting a lot, like she’d been running in
the park. Mom was kneeling beside her, stroking the top of her head. “What
happened?” I asked. “She just started whimpering all of a sudden,” said Via,
kneeling down next to Mom. I looked down at Mom, who was crying,
too. “I’m taking her to the animal hospital downtown,” she said. “The taxi’s
coming to pick me up.” “The vet will make her better, right?” I said. Mom looked at me.
“I hope so, honey,” she said quietly.
“But I honestly don’t know.” “Of course he will!” I said. “Daisy’s been sick a lot
lately, Auggie. And she’s old “But they can fix her,” I said, looking at Via to agree
with me, but Via wouldn’t look up at me.
Mom’s lips were trembling. “I think it might be time we
say goodbye to Daisy, Auggie. I’m sorry.” “No!” I said. “We don’t want her to suffer,
Auggie,” she said. The phone rang. Via picked it up, said, “Okay, thanks,” and then
hung up. “The taxi’s outside,” she said, wiping her tears with the backs of her
hands. “Okay, Auggie, open the door for me, sweetie?” said Mom, picking Daisy up very
gently like she was a huge droopy baby.
“Please, no, Mommy?” I cried, putting myself in front of the
door. “Honey, please,” said Mom. “She’s very heavy.” “What about Daddy?” I cried. “He’s
meeting me at the hospital,” Mom said. “He doesn’t want dizzy to suffer, Auggie.” Via
moved me away from the door and held it
open for Mom. “My cell phone’s on if you need anything,” Mom said to Via. “Can you
cover her with the blanket?” Via nodded, but she was crying hysterically now. “Say
goodbye to Daisy, kids,” Mom said, tears streaming down her face. “I love you, Daisy,”
Via said, kissing Daisy on the nose. “I love you so much.” “Bye, little girly I whispered into
Daisy’s ear. “I love you. Mom carried Daisy down the stew The taxi driver had opened
the back door and we watched her get in.
Just before she closed the door, Mom looked up at us standing by the entrance
to the building and she gave us a little
wave. I don’t think I’ve ever seen her look sadder.
“I love you, Mommy!” said Via. “I love you, Mommy!” I said. “I’m sorry,
Mommy!” Mom blew a kiss to us and closed the door. We watched the car leave and
then Via closed the door. She looked at me a second, and then she hugged me very,
very tight while we both cried a million tears
[Music]